A Guide to the Howdershell/Hummer Family Collection, 1904-c.1940s
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Howdershell/Hummer Family Collection, 1904-c.1940s
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 07-28
0.75 linear feet
The Howdershell/Hummer Family Collection consists of 0.75 linear feet and spans the years 1904-c.1940s and contains correspondence, family genealogies, and photographs. The bulk of the correspondence is between Lucile Howdershell Hummer and Beverly T. Hummer.
Howdershell and Hummer Families
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Donated by Karen Hummer Fort, March 2021.
Historical and Biographical Information
Lucile Howdershell was born on February 27, 1888 in Bealton, Virginia to James E. Howdershell (1846-1928) and Amanda S. Nalls Howdershell (1854-1933). Lucile was one of nine children. In 1899, the Howdershells moved to Lincolnia, Virginia in Fairfax County.
Around 1913, Beverly Traylor Hummer began courting Lucile Howdershell. Hummer was born on December 20, 1886 in Falls Church, Virginia to Benjamin A. Hummer (1857-1946) and Mary Ida Brunner Hummer (1856-1925). The Hummer family of Fairfax County is the namesake of present-day Hummer Road in Annandale, Virginia. Beverly was employed as a steam fitter for the Giesboro Steel Works in Giesboro, Maryland before serving in World War I with the 5th Company 5th Engineer Training Regiment.
Beverly and Lucile maintained a constant correspondence as evidenced by the letters in this collection. They were married on June 30, 1919 at the Howdershell home in Lincolnia. The couple went on to have two sons, Beverly T. Hummer, Jr. and Richard J. Hummer. Beverly was a plumbing and heating contractor until his death on October 28, 1951.
Lucile was active in the community with the Woman’s Missionary Union of the First Baptist Church of Alexandria, Lincolnia Women’s Club, and Lincolnia Parent Teachers Association. She died on October 20, 1978 in Manassas, Virginia. The couple are both buried at Ivy Hill Cemetery in Alexandria.
Lucile Howdershell Hummer’s sister, Minnie Howdershell (1876-1970), married William Lee Clark (1863-1952) in 1902. That same year, Clark built the Clark House which is presently owned by the Fairfax County Park Authority and located at 6332 Barcroft Mews Drive in Falls Church, Virginia.
Scope and Content
The Howdershell/Hummer Family Collection consists of 0.75 linear feet and spans the years 1904-c.1940s and contains correspondence, family genealogies, and photographs. The bulk of the correspondence is between Lucile Howdershell Hummer and Beverly T. Hummer. Subjects include family life and properties in Lincolnia, Virginia.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1904-1922, Boxes 1-2
This series contains letters chiefly between Lucile Howdershell Hummer and Beverly T. Hummer before and after their marriage. Subjects discussed are family life in Lincolnia, Virginia; personal matters; local events; World War I; and the flu epidemic. Letters from Lucile’s brother, Bedford Howdershell, are also included. The letters are arranged chronologically. Some letters are undated but were inserted by the donor into the chronological order based on their written contents.
Series 2: Family Genealogy, 1928, Box 2
This series contains typed and handwritten family genealogies for the Howdershell and Nalls families. Also included is a newspaper obituary for James E. Howdershell.
Series 3: Photographs, 1935-c. 1940s, Box 2
This series contains photographs of Howdershell family members. Also included are family properties including the Howdershell House “Edgmoor” on Lincolnia Road and the Clark House owned by Minnie Howdershell Clark. Photographs are arranged alphabetically.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
None
None
Index Terms
Howdershell family; Howdershell, Bedford J. (1876-1940); Hummer family; Hummer, Beverly T. (1886-1951); Hummer, Lucile Howdershell (1888-1978); Lincolnia (Va.) - History
Container List
- Series 1: Correspondence, 1904-1922
  - Letter, Bedford Howdershell to Lucile Howdershell, 1904 June 19 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter, Dick to "Bluffer", 1911 July 18 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1913 November 10 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1913 November 24 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer [4 letters in envelope], 1915 July (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1916 February 3 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1916 April 6 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letter, Beverly T. Hummer to Lucile Howdershell, 1916 April 9 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1916 April 14 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letter, Beverly T. Hummer to Lucile Howdershell, 1916 April 25 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1916 April 28 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letter, Beverly T. Hummer to Lucile Howdershell, 1916 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1916 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1916 May 21 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1916 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1916 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1916 June 13 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1916 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1916 September 25 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1916 October 2 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Letter, Beverly T. Hummer to Lucile Howdershell [fragments], 1916 December 7 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Letter, Beverly T. Hummer to Lucile Howdershell, 1917 May 24 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1917 November 22 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1917 December (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Letter, Beverly T. Hummer to Lucile Howdershell, 1917 December 13 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1918 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1918 March 14 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1918 March 19 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1918 March 20 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1918 March 25 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1918 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1918? May 18 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1918 July 19 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1918 July 22 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Letter, Beverly T. Hummer to Lucile Howdershell, 1918 October 1 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Letter, Beverly T. Hummer to Lucile Howdershell, 1918 October 17 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, Undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1918 November 8 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1918 November 25 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1918 November 27 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1918 December 4 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Letter, Beverly T. Hummer to Lucile Howdershell, 1918 December 11 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Letter, Beverly T. Hummer to Lucile Howdershell, 1918 December 20 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, 1919 February 11 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer, Undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Letter, Beverly T. Hummer to Lucile Howdershell, 1919 April 28 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Letter, Beverly T. Hummer to Lucile Howdershell, 1919 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Letter, Bedford Howdershell to Lucile Howdershell, 1919 June 3 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell Hummer to Beverly T. Hummer, 1920 May 27 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell Hummer to Beverly T. Hummer, Undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell Hummer to Bedford Howdershell, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Letter, Beverly T. Hummer to Lucile Howdershell Hummer, 1920 November 15 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell Hummer to Beverly T. Hummer, 1921 February 14 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell Hummer to Beverly T. Hummer, 1921 March 7 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell Hummer to Beverly T. Hummer, 1921 March 10 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell Hummer to Beverly T. Hummer, 1921 March 16 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Letters, Beverly T. Hummer to Lucile Howdershell Hummer [fragments], 1921 March 28 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Envelopes, Beverly T. Hummer to Lucile Howdershell Hummer, 1921 March (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell Hummer to Beverly T. Hummer, 1921 March 29 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell Hummer to Beverly T. Hummer, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell Hummer to Beverly T. Hummer, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell Hummer to Beverly T. Hummer, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letter, Lucile Howdershell Hummer to Beverly T. Hummer, 1921 April 11 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letter, Bedford Howdershell to Amanda Howdershell, 1922 September (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Notecard, Lucile & Beverly T. Hummer to Amanda & James Howdershell, 1922 October 8 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Partial letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer(?), Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Partial letter, Lucile Howdershell to Beverly T. Hummer(?), Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series 2: Family Genealogy, Undated, 1928
  - Howdershell Family Genealogy, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Nall-Nalle-Naul-Nalls Family Genealogy, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Obituary, James E. Howdershell, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Series 3: Photographs, Undated, 1935-c. 1940s
  - Photo, Amanda and James Howdershell, Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Photo, Amanda and James Howdershell, Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Photo, Amanda Howdershell, Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Photo, Bedford Howdershell, Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Photo, Clarence E. Howdershell, Undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Photo, Clarence Howdershell, Maude Howdershell, and Lucile Howdershell at "Resthaven", Undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Photo, Clark House (Minnie May Clark), Undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Photo, Ellie Howdershell, Maude Howdershell, and Lucile Howdershell, Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Photo, Howdershell Family - Minnie, Bedford, Julian, Clarence, John, Lucile, Maude, Ellie, Amanda, James and Ralph Howdershell, Undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Photo, Howdershell House "Edgemoor" on Lincolnia Road (demolished 1959), Undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Photo, Jacob Howdershell, Undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Photo, Lucile Howdershell, Undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Photo, Lucile Howdershell and Maude Howdershell(?), Undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Photo, Lucile Howdershell Hummer and Beverly Hummer, c. 1940s. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Photo, M. Amanda Susan Nalls and James Erastus Howdershell, Undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Photo, Minnie May Clark, 1935 July 2 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Photo, Minnie May Clark, Brenda(?), and Whitney Clark, Undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Photo, Octavia Howdershell, Undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Photo, Ralph Howdershell, Undated (Box 2, Folder 31)